謝大衞。
Thank you, Mr. President.
That， I apologise.
Unfortunately, just look around.
為人民謀幸福，多謝主席。
for lending us days to this three days debates.
Their kind and conscious efforts are not being reciprocated by members across the floor.
First, I like to thank the CS, FS and Secretary for Justice, and all the government officials.
Either.
two o two one。
does not offer.
Let me start.
much ground for optimism.
My speech, with the big picture.
我會 tackles the specifics of the policy address later.
2020， was branded the worst year for Hong Kong SAR.
和經濟困局。
居民們有繼續受苦。
Our economic outlook is dire.
300百億， have come and gone.
三rounds of relief efforts，costing up to。
It has been reported that people are quitting the city in droves.
The S.A.R. has never been so isolated in the global arena.
香港是 undeniable in the midst of a confidence crisis.
但我們係比之前在2020年更差。
自Chief Executive's policy address to this Council last November。
Mr. President, the unemployment is edging up to 6.7, and very likely to go higher.
as the financial secretary admitted, in his latest blog, the worst has yet to come in the year of the ox.
Hong Kong definitely and truly is an island. Fortunately, we are backed by the peninsula with our motherland behind.
gym、beauty parlours、massage parlours、education centres、retail outlets、bars、restaurants and many others are on the verge of collapse.
If they have not folded yet, those who can hang on to their jobs are often required to go on no pay leave or have their wages slashed.
However, officials are in no mood for further substantial relief initiatives. That I understand, another round of assistance under the unemployment support scheme.
我 always punctual.
has been brewed out.
The monthly salaries, Mr. President.
not a single political appointee.
We need to save people, not the park.
The Information Services Department awarded.
Calls for emergency fund for the jobless have gone unheeded.
其他地方有，我有見政治在行動，up close for nearly half a century.
Where is our Hong Kong rescue plan for the present and the post-COVID-19? Singapore had it.
inside that bureaucratic cocoon, job security and benefits that go with it are protected.
They don't hear the collective cry for help. They don't feel the pain. They simply sitting on their hands.
The average families in Hong Kong are suffering in plain sight. Our leaders somehow fail to see the urgency.
has been account, has been held accountable for the social turmoil and the many missteps in the fight against the epidemic.
Let me remind our top officials that cogent and popular policies start with heart. Without empathy, words are empty.
They are more eager in saving Ocean Park than alleviating the sufferings of the 250,000 unemployed and those on the verge of bankruptcies.
Now I like to talk about the revival of Hong Kong economy. Now that the vaccines against the coronavirus is on the way, there is a glimmer of hope. We should start thinking and thinking ahead to put Hong Kong back on track and back on the map. Last summer.
But.
Have been.
by and large， restored。
so far have at best been feeble.
Nevertheless，absence of confrontation。
On social media, the chief secretary.
Meanwhile， the attempts in this regard。
On the service alone, it's not enough to put Hong Kong back on its feet.
since the national security law was passed in place last June, law and order.
For administration have written through the Washington Post to protest against the American sanctions.
We have yet to see whether the foreign spin doctors game plan for Hong Kong is worth the salt.
努力去 reboot Hong Kong，會有要被 grounded on an authentic process of social conciliation.
This is hardly any coordination behind those apparently isolated haphazard PR moves.
thanks to the police, this there is hardly any mass protests, let alone organised violence on the street.
一US dollar六點三million dollars to a public relations firm clouded in controversies over its works for Saudi Arabia.
Brand Hong Kong have advertised on how wonderful our supply chain is. The CEO and her adviser and chief cordial exchange over high tea.
是 not one of them.
Policy address in 2017.
Nobody in the administration has responded.
none of the policy secretaries have stepped forward to take responsibility.
她説：，was not the right time to tackle electoral reform and other political problems.
The CE silence in the policy address on how to reconnect with the people, especially the young, is deafening.
Like it or not, it is no longer viable for the C and some other high officials to visit our key trading partners in the world.
investor confidence and action plans need to be devised asap so that it can be activated any time.
There is never a perfect timing. The best time is now. Give us certainty. Give us stability. And give us harmony.
It will be a waste of time to ask the world to reinvest in Hong Kong, to come to Hong Kong, while Hongkongers are not convinced about our own future.
If they had the chance, I hope this is also wrong. Some 50% have set in motion their migration plan. Our social scientists have done their bit to sound the alarm.
Once international travel more or less resumes normal, the C.E.N.R. de facto ambassador should be busy visiting major international partners to dispel political rumours, clear misconceptions and re-instill.
The Hankang University has looked into the issue. Almost half of the nearly two thousand residents they interview deemed the city's earlier dialogue sessions with the public as having zero effect in easing social grievances.
Her engagement attempts were rated with an average of just 2.5 out of a scale of 10. Ironically, Mr. President, the research was funded by PICO, the Policy Innovation and Coordination Office, which was a baby of the EU's inaugural inaugural.
Another PECO sponsored survey indicated almost ninety percent of our high school students do not trust the administration. Really sad to see this. Similar studies abound. A Chinese university poll revealed that alarming forty four percent of our residents would emigrate.
We must give residents of all political stripes a real sense of belonging and ownership in Hong Kong. There are many ways to do so. Obliging companies to create 2,000 temporary government subsidies subsidised jobs in the Greater Bay Area for Hong Kong youngster for 18
how exactly?
We must break this vicious circle.
It is a fact of life that no guest would like to visit.
within three years for those on the housing authority waiting list.
The following proposed domestic policies, I believe, are step in the right direction.
such stop-gap projects are welcome and are meant to last for only a few years.
政府是承諾提供租金補貼，和15,000個過渡性居屋單位。
我唔 have a crystal ball，Mr President，whether Biden would be as hostile as his predecessor is anybody's guess。
It is the sea duty to chart out a healing process. She and she alone is in the position to do so.
Making it easier for the needy to get onto the first rank of the leader, the government has opted to create one more rank at the bottom.
But I am certain that sanctions and counter sanctions are bound to set Hong Kong on a path of harm and decline.
To do this is beyond me. In any case, initiatives to restore the SAR image must be premised on a more harmonised Hong Kong society.
Some forward thinking is needed to attend to practical issues. Who will? Who else have the standing to step into her shoes to lead our revival campaign, particularly in the West?
一貧窮、多功能、家，像 ours at the moment， multiple social indicators inform us that Hong Kong is far from having recovered politically since 2009.
They will show that the top echelon of power is prepared to see things from the perspective of the people. Now I turn on the issue on housing. Apart from politics, which we had more than enough, housing is a top mind social concern.
一 decent home will bring a long way in cultivating residents' sense of attachment. The government's approach has been unfortunately remained piecemeal. The city is intent on building a so-called housing ladder to help residents to move from one rank to the other, instead of
to no surprise, lengthened.
The average waiting time for general applicants.
each until the private landowners take back the sites.
The ratio will be lower to no more than fifty percent.
The last time I check, the queue for public rental units have.
accommodating to facilitate down payment and help those who can afford to buy.
second，cancel the special stamp duty，the lux，the ce are keen。
as I said earlier is 5.6 years, and there's no likelihood that it will be shortened.
她 is amended that private units are still beyond the reach of the average family. That's true.
extra five thousand transitional units a year is hardly a solution.
to keep the aboriginal stamp duty, special stamp duty, buy stamp duty, which were introduced as cooling measures a decade ago.
個homebuyer without mortgage insurance plan can only be given a loan of 60% of the property value, or a maximum of 5 million.
The issues of shortening the waiting time of 5.6 years and the adequate supply of housing rental units have left unfulfilled.
There are over one hundred and fifty-four thousand general applicants for rental housing, and another hundred and three thousand non-elderly one-person files under the quota and point system.
一 more direct and effective approach to boost housing mobility is to resuscitate the sluggish market of used private secondary flats. There are two ways to do so. First, lift the loan-to-value cap. At present, a potential
If the price of flat is above ten million, the restriction have make it difficult for families to climb up the housing ladder by purchasing their first private flats. The cap will last relax in August two thousand and two. There is room for the loan to value ratio to be more.
什麼構成呢？
such residential.
be relaxed, perhaps in phrases, freezing those.
to revitalise the market， the various duties could first.
In two o two o is forty thousand, including both sixty thousand, including both.
instead， they suggested that the rates on residential units could be increased with exemption from local residents.
這些市場限制已經成為反導向的，在維持所謂的住房樓梯不阻塞。
Residential property transactions. Thank you, FS, for lifting the non-residential ratio recently in the market.
the first and second hand, that is a drastic fall in supply, and that's why push all the the the the
Attempt to supply flats in Hong Kong to zero, the special duties have made it much better for people to own their first-hand homes.
fact is because whether we like it or not, it's the high land price policy. Secondly, the government's measures, and thirdly, it's the low interest rates.
duties have suppressed short-term supply in the market and failed to have any cooling effect as the government intended. Instead, they suggested that the rise
I'm tempted to say, great minds think alike. In 2020, transactions, annual transactions for housing, including first and second hand, was 150,000 units.
The outdated duties have stifled the private market. I have been telling the government that the same over the years since 2010, only to be snubbed and ignored. That I can take it. It is worse than talking to a brick wall.
幾天前，香港大學商學院發表一份經濟政策綠皮書。背後的文件是香港最頂尖的經濟學家，藉助他們的實證經驗，他們指出各種措施的副作用。
from the stamp duty of a cost of ten million or above before they are eventually being ditched. Instead of imposing artificial hurdles, officials should set their eyes on a steady supply of a subsidised rental housing units and leave private transactions.
Of neither here nor there.
to the devices of the market forces.
實用價值應該，當然要被保全。
where were the plan for the famous CY lungs?
Scheme at the fringe of the green park housing over.
Now I look into the another aspect, the land supply.
However, sites at the fringe of the remaining green area could be tapped for public housing.
我 also concur with the Hong Kong U professors to re-activate the connection between public housing.
over twenty twenty or thirty thousand housing units, they were abandoned at the minute when.
The chief executive took office. Why? Explain to the public. Couple of the 720 hectares.
market of the private one, they can done through privatising public rental housing, sell all the rental housing to those tenants and make them responsible and make them feel that they have that sense of ownership.
It is official projections are reliable. If official projections are reliable, we will need three hundred and thirty hectares to build three hundred three hundred and sixteen thousand public housing units over the next decade.
Of the brownfield clusters, yet to have a development timetable, there will be ample supply of land to see us through the next few decades, until perhaps the tomorrow land tower vision is materialised to meet further demands.
this the secretary of housing have done much work and for this we are thankful, but it is a scramble to meet the demand. The government has opted to take away one fifth of Funan golf course, of which I am a member, to make room for public housing. Construction is scheduled for completion by 202.
我正提供9,000公眾住房單位，這是慘痛，到少於3%的目標，但一110年曆的遺產將被毀滅，不可逆轉。在這個過程中，這是典型的政府政策。
香港 has a land area of 1,111 square kilometres, or 1.1 million hectares. Woodlands, scrubland, grassland, wetland have make up 75% of our land. Green belts with the biodiversity and environment.
percent increase. That's substantial in today's
which is listed on the local exchange.
expenses in excess of $200.
一個預定義的生產力因素。
一 monopoly，the M P I itself has grown into an independent empire.
costing government over budget, over time in some of the major.
under the wing of the government, the rail system has become dominant mode of mass transit.
這 arrangement are meant to alleviate the public burden of transport expenses during the epidemic.
rail projects，the government is a 75% shareholder of MTRC。
八 Billion Dollars ended up we pay over sixteen Billion Dollars and taking a longer time of three years.
The end result is that fares have only one direction to go, Mr President, and is always going up and never downward.
Temporary discounts and subsidies type of epidemic are quick fix for a few months. What the people want is to put the genie back into the bottle.
官員 assigned to the corporation board of directors are outnumbered and have failed to prevent the many delays and overspending in its major rail development project. Take a case in point: the West Cowlam station fixed-price contract at
The C.E. announced the concession with a degree of pride. Thank her. Despite the showdown and rest, MTR has chalk up a revenue of 19.94 billion dollars from its Hong Kong transport operation, representing a 2.3
Now, Mr. President, I still have time. I look into transport. The MTR Corporation have extended the 20% fare discount for three months until March. Thank you, Mr. Secretary. The government will continue to subsidise up to one third or $400 per month of individual transport.
Climate, its fair hike are not overseen by either the LCH or the XCO. Instead, the company is entitled to a direct drive formula on the basis of composite consumer price index, the nominal price wage index, the N.
係。
this is。
to cover。
hence the delay.
它 has gone with a glitch.
debt financing and our secretary.
could actually guide you in this. This.
this is two years after it was proposed.
The bureaucracy needs a year to get it done.
those aged be be between sixty and sixty four.
However, like many other well-intended policies of this administration.
once and for all, Mr. Secretary, MTR market capitalisation is estimated at 277 billion dollars.
The secretary for labour and social welfare told us that the extension would not be in place at least until early next year.
personalised octopus card with users' photos are to be issued for each of the 600,000 senior citizen who stand to benefit.
政府買back會 cost 約 16 億美元， funding 可以 通過一 spin off of properties of MTR and also 通過。
I think will be money for value to showcase the government's commitment to people's livelihood in the uncertain times now and in the future. Next one, I like to touch on the two dollars scheme for the elderly, sixty to sixty four. I applaud the expansion of the two dollars transport fare scheme.
The case.
Further delay, it's official. So insist.
not proportional. The ratio of donation to the administration cost is, to put it mildly.
被cross check again dishonestly， the entire government machinery would have been bogged down.
Now I like to, in the presence of the secretary of justice, I like to talk about the Nina Wang's charity fund.
我有The Late Nina Wang's estate in mind. The estate comprises the assets under the umbrella of the Wahmaw Group.
In contrast, the fee for administrators of the estate is a stunning six-deep million dollars a year. That's
Official time and energy will be put to better use to look for additional means and resources to see the territory through the economic downturn.
except otherwise prescribed by law or ordered by the court, the charity may operate autonomously and decide how it to inform the public about its operation.
perception. In any case, trust is a two-way street. If officials treat citizens with suspicion and without respect, they too will end up being mistrusted.
disturbing. The secretary for justice is the legal guardian of charitable interests. She was asked in this chamber about the undesirable status of affairs of the Wan District.
她 is obviously reluctant to intervene, and understandably, under normal circumstances, charity should be left to operate under their restrictive governing articles. According to the secretary of justice.
The card for personal photos can still be issued as planned. A grace period of one year or so to offer the benefits now will go a long way to earn the goodwill of the elderly and the younger generation.
as at last September thirty, the group was valued at one hundred and forty one billion dollars. From two hundred and one eight to two hundred and two zero, China Camp has made a donation to charity purposes at the aggregate sum of twenty six point six million last year, a mere five million dollars.
這係一個褻瀆到長ablish honour system， which relies primarily on the integrity of those concerned. The principles have been working well in so many areas in the public domain. Public officers' declaration of additional duty is an example. If every submission, a declaration to to
abuses cannot be denied, cannot be avoided in any system. The question is whether countermeasures are worth the time and administrative cost. Random spot checks on the elderly and reasonable penalties will survive. The two dollar scheme should be implemented without.
citizen。
Can make up for some.
nowadays it is trendy.
say true to one's original aspiration.
Now I have running out time. I just like to touch on the budget.
to ask for suggestions to for the next dish.
will extend our full cooperation to make it happen.
我 have just set out mine in the above paragraph.
When we look for vision and leadership at such a critical juncture,
I'm sorry to confess, I'm disappointed. I hope the upcoming budget.
The policy address should have expounded on ways to boost morale and confidence.
要 empower the authority to assume a proactive role. I can guarantee the Secretary for Justice that my fellow legislator.
Let this charity do charity well, and help the unemployed 250,000 and employed.
On hand is far from being normal. The estate could have been a major funding source to supplement government's relief packages. If a new law is needed.
Of the last ground in the 167 paragraph policy blueprint, our financial secretary has dressed himself as a master chef.
whatever these aspirations are, they have been clouded by the present political uncertainty, economic dogma, challenges to the rule of law, and some may add an erosion of our society core values.
啫。
謝偉俊業。
實際上咧，管理嘅人。
主席，我係代主席，我歡迎你翻嚟嚇，我誒。
有啲好全世界最大嘅寶石啊，鑽喺度啊，有啲spell喺度咧。
Help us, need us to cope with the new realities, both local and global. Thank you.
完全唔擔心喺喺會外咧，都係好多好多地方咧，係完全質實化咗我所講嘅指控咧，就係話成件事係混帳。
We will soon, we will know soon enough whether he could cook to the taste of the people and for the people, Mr. President.
My time is coming up. I support the motion to thank the C E for working very hard for Hong Kong, but one could only wish that you could also work smarter as well to lead us.
個施政報告咧就拖遲咗做啦，亦都係就喺十講到十十二月出發表嘅，到而家咧都可能有過多嘅時間咧。疫情上又過咗少少秒啦，情況咧比似乎咧。
If adopted, I believe there will be more conducive to sending the right signal to the people that the government cares, and I believe they do cares. The FRS is a self-made man, given his humble background. I hope he would be more sensitive to the needs of the needy.
多謝主席。主席，我或者回應下剛才阿石領員啱啱講啦。噉我聽到佢講話誒，官員就好多啦。不過咧，就似乎議員咧就唔係好reciprocate，唔係好好因好啊，或者誒回應翻官員嘅咁多人踴躍。不過可以擔保咁多位官員閣下咧，我哋議員咧其實係好多係坐。
房裏邊睇緊疫情之下咧，包括我本人都好啦，一路都睇住個過程，所以就我相信唔需要陳啟元咧就過分地擔心呢一樣嘢。第二樣咧，因為佢啱啱講完關於華茂基金咧，用喺我喺呢個位咧，就都插把嘴講下先。誒，我完全咧hundred percent support啊支持啊陳啟元所講咧，如果需要立法嘅話咧。
可能一個最簡單嘅方法咧，最可能仲快添，因為呢度咧實在一塌糊塗，太混帳啦！啱啱先講緊又有個誒訴訟咧，又話要告誒追究翻咩四億管理費，根本就係蛇鼠一窩，根本就係有筆咁大筆錢咧。我唔知係好似我哋以往睇歷史故事咧，有啲。
嗰啲錢咧，你掂親咧都會死嘅一樣。而家呢個基金咧，就好似咁多年嚟咧，嗨親都死嘅，因為可能係有裏邊真係有啲不義之財又好，有啲好多問題又好，反正咧成件事就係真係混帳一鋪。我希望咧誒律政司司長呢方面咧，就真係要孭起呢件事咧，唔好再畀個混帳落去，因為。
誒喺度好多上下棋手，連嗰啲噉嘅專業工、專業嘅會計核數、似乎嘅執業嘅核數師都喺度咧，好多問題出現咗嘅。噉我唔想過分嘅濫用咗我呢個立法會嘅特權，因為噉我所講清啲嘢都，如果唔係呢度講咧，都可能會有問題。但係事實上咧，我完。
我哋唔係work from home。
我哋係真係要落手落腳咧，睇好多嘢。我哋收多電話嘅，嗰啲平時係。
換開換式咁講咧，嗰啲嘅Jack嘅局長咧，就佢哋可能所感覺唔到，因為佢哋可能太多理性喺度，冇感性冇心喺度。
施政報告出台嘅時候咧，仲更加嚴峻。噉啊，我轉頭嘅機會咧，我就都會講講咧。但係我先先講講咧，就我哋而家情況點先。
講政治，你唔識針對人心嘅諗法，你唔識畀市民有個同理心感覺咧，你就根本就唔適合做特首，甚至高官都唔適合做，因為你唔可以噉樣做。
期啊！所以我哋咧係唔能夠過分地太過淨係講話我哋自己個道理性，因為你哋真係唔明啊！公務員係身高量準㗎，你哋work from home咧，對好多市民嚟講咧係真係唔使做啊！
因為你任何主要政策，你唔識包裝，你唔講政治，就係唔係好嘅政策就咁簡單。所以呢個講法我好想好同意啊！陳勤議員離開咗啦，佢講法就話即係噉嘅啫，咁即係我我係好同好有心度感。所以我哋接觸到市民。
你在在座嘅高官，你哋梗係要做啦。我知道，因為你決策官員咧，唔好話你哋官員啦，就算相對高層嘅，甚話如果係做professional專責人，即係嗰啲專業人士咧，包括我咁多年嚟都係咧，我哋從來都唔需要擔心呢一樣嘢，因為我哋廿四小時都係我哋嘅mind係working。
我哋香港咧就其實比起全世界疫情就唔算話真係做得太差，起碼我哋死人方面啊，我哋疫嗰個確診數字方面咧，確診數字方面咧都唔係話名列前茅。不過香港最慘嘅地方咧，直到近日嘅美國為止嚇，最慘嘅地方咧就係疫情之前咧，我哋有天災。
依搞咗我哋年成年嘅時間咧，依香港係疲弱不堪嘅。咁當然有啲人就話啊，而家見到美國都係噉，就有啲少少開心翻。當然我哋唔希望噉樣，但係香港係世界上其中一個地方咧，係天災人禍打孖嚟嘅。連續係兩年幾咧，我哋係完全冇機會喘息過嘅。所以咧，呢個噉嘅施政報告咧，市民有期望嘅，佢哋期望。
講咧喺史無前例嘅天災人禍之下咧，我哋咧就有一個喘息嘅機會，有啲曙光啊，或者用我上一陣語言所講嘅咩幸福感啦嚇噉。但係咧就呢個拖遲咗一個多月嘅施政報告咧，係明顯咧係冇乜畀到我哋市民，特別我哋基層，甚或我哋中產市民有呢種噉嘅感覺，有。
啲曙光嘅感覺，我誒曾經都或者大不偉地咧喺特首施政報告出咗之後咧，第一次嘅質詢答問大會咧，我就同特首講咧，我話喂呢份報告係有遠景冇現景噉啊誒，仲有將來式就冇乜現在式咁噉，的而且確咧就我都或者再stand by我講。
講法，事實上咧，再睇翻件事咧，我哋好似喺平行時空生活緊噉。誒，好多嘢咧，我哋好似唔覺得，我哋社會上咧係真係好大問題發生咗噉。當然睇翻啲股票投資咧，似乎就真係好似係咁喎。但係實際上生活上，我哋所接觸到嘅市民，即係唔係誒當初阿陳啟賢所。
因為我亦都留意到咧，就無論啊特首喺佢施政報告裏邊講喺疫疫疫情又好，或者好多時佢答問大會都好啦，成日都強調一樣嘢就係話咧，我哋係講數據啊，講科學，呢個理性嘅分析嘅政策嘅理性咧係應該嘅。但係作為一個管理人，作為最高層嘅管理人咧，你多多少少都唔能夠。
啊。
係。
真係離曬地。
來生不發，來生不返觀堂宮啊！
我講咗成七分鐘，就係講呢樣嘢，對唔住啊，主席誒。
香港係點咧？對唔住，我哋咁低點算咧？好啦，我講翻我近翻近翻啲我嘅選區先，係九龍東。
我諗全世界都真係覺得會話嚇，係咪做出嚟㗎？不過好在哈佛自己做嘅啫，好在一個長時間做嘅啫。如果唔係嘅話，又話我哋做假數㗎啦。
相比起我哋誒國家嗰個誒哈佛，大家都知道哈佛嗰個報告咧，就連續嚇二零一三、二零一六年八次調查嘅average嘅平均咧九十三點一。
即係我相信呢啲可能多少有少少戲言啦，但係事實上咧，我唔希望大家咧過分地強調九龍東咧係一個成功嘅例子，因為事實上咧係個非常之慘嘅一個情況，都唔好講災情先。
講翻我哋誒嗰個民意調查啦，我同事幫我準備嗰啲數字啦，我都hea好快咁講講啦。即係剛才都好多同事提過㗎啦，琴日都提過㗎啦，話我哋嗰個施政報告唔滿二六十四percent啦，評分廿七點二percent，呢啲我唔唔需要多講啦，係有紀錄以來最低嘅，對唔住。
因為我哋自己咩飛，我哋又唔擔心呢一樣嘢。但係對於好多中層嘅公務員嚟講咧，work from home就真係等於緊韌腳嘅啫。而更加慘咧，對於嗰啲出面街嘅市民，佢哋嘅感官啊，就係佢哋冇工做、冇生意做、咩都做唔到嘅時候咧，覺得公務員咧。
成日話我唔講政治，因為政治就係所有一切嚟嘅。即係如果你過分地好偏政治，好似真當然大我大家知道可能唔係真嘅啦。但係如果真係真係噉嘅話，你咁乾淨咩都唔敢講政治嘅話，你就一定揩嘢。因為事實上全世界都係講政治，所有嘢處理都係政治，人心都係政治。你唔講。
中產喊住打嚟話：我份工冇咗，我唔知點算。嗰啲唔同你講咩制度完整啊，局長啊，許局長，你話成日講咩M P F嗰啲，轉頭我講啦。你成日話咩制度完整啊嗰啲噉樣，理性個個都知道啊。我都知道退休嘅制度係點樣，但係而家呢個係非常時。
咁所以咧，我我我係希望我我唔我即係咁講，希望唔好過分地即係誒，逼執到太多公務原因，我唔係噉嘅意思。但係事實上，我想話畀大家聽咧，個感覺係點樣。所以呢方面咧，我哋要敏感，我哋唔能夠唔講政治，因為政治係人心嘅一部分。所以希望咧，大家做嘢嗰陣時。
咧都係政策之餘咧，理性之餘咧，講講政治，因為政治就係人性啊，就好多嘢喺裏邊，包括剛才陳一強議員所講嘅嗰啲咩啊，損上益下四個字就好聽㗎啦，損上益下，我好贊成㗎。呢個時候你要畀人感覺到你係損上益下，起碼做講啊、做啊、感官都係要噉樣。
誒。
好多啊！
嗰啲點算啊？更加點算啊？
佢只係一個行政人員，咁咪死得啦！
我想大家講呢句説話之前咧，諗一諗嗰啲連一個鐵飯碗都冇嗰啲工家庭。
誒，即係我我對唔住，我可能個時間我要再馬上講其他嘢，誒。
税税税，因為咧呢排咧就誒，除咗除咗税之外，有預繳税啦。我知道政府嘅立場嘅line take計劃，唔係啊，你申請我哋可以延遲交税，我哋畀你啊，冇問題啊，噉。
用翻啊！我有個朋友，我我哋嘅才子啦，最先講佢口頭禪嘅啦，come on咁即係嚇要扮佢口音，即係你唔好噉樣啦，大佬好啦，油輪碼頭。
誒更加你話啊，而家如果公務員派畀佢哋畀個人工，佢哋咧佢哋會肯使錢啲嘅喎。哇！呢個又有即係好多時就係講政治啦，即係感官上噉係咪即係話公公務員收嘅人工，佢先會使錢，佢啲先係錢咧？
如果你交畀嗰啲私人市場嘅勞工，佢哋嗰啲錢係唔使嘅咧，或者佢哋啲命係咪即係冇咁好命咧？即係嗱呢啲你即係永遠都係我哋講政治就要考呢啲噉嘅，要一定要諗。咁呢樣嘢咧就有排講，因為事實上我哋嘅特首剛才講啦，佢話唔中意政治。
誒損上益下嘅問題，我我明白到，當然唔係所有公務員都係好well off嘅，都有啲係真係掹掹緊嘅。但係如果你話由於因為你哋屋企有一個公務員鐵飯碗啊，不過我太太我仔女可能冇喎，都裁員咗喎，咁點算咧？
我可能要好快跳我另一個題目，即係講我一個誒都追好多次嘅項目啦。大家都可能期待緊我講呢樣嘢，強積金嘅問題。不過事實上咧，呢排市民咧，除強積金之外咧，佢哋最關心咧就係交税。
馬上有啲即刻可以好快起到屋嘅地方嚟，搞掂呢一嚿嘢咧，我諗成個九龍東生曬地又多，中中短期地多咗。噉啊，至於其他嗰啲咧，我相信咧就誒嗰個P P P P，我今日唔夠時間講啦，不過有機會即係講下嗰個明日大廈嗰個項目咧，我都係有啲意見睇法嘅。
個報告咧，我見到但係篇幅咧就好開心咧，就話我哋有個叫起動九龍東好成功啦，做藍盤啦，跟住我哋有個叫誒躍動港島南啦。由於港島區係我區議會選區誒一部分啦，誒誒有份啦，九龍東更加係我嘅嘅嘅基誒基本盤啦嚇。咁所以我用喺我喺度講講，即係就。
呢一種我唔知咩人需要包裝啊，定還是即係當然引惡揚善咁嘢。但係對唔住啊，九龍東唔係一個成功嘅例子啊。起動九龍東係變咗蠕動九龍東啊。如果你話講跳躍動啊，港島南咧可能會咗塞爆港島南，因為兩件嘢咧可能都唔係好事嚟。我先講九龍東先啦，我哋而家。
不嬲話要想做第二個CBD喺觀觀塘咧，又話架空系統啊，又話誒依樣嗰樣，但係到而家為止真係見唔到一個成效出嚟，反而就係越搞就越大禍。誒，我用下啲冇咁離地嘅網上嘅字眼啦，即係話佢咩掠食天堂啊，咩翻工地獄啊，咩。
花咗咁多錢落去啊！我哋曾經都弱笑佢，就即係西伯利亞九龍西伯利亞啦嚇噉，但係即係似乎真係真係唔掂啊！到而家為止仲係唔掂噉，我都曾經建議話整條橋啊誒誒，依樣嗰樣啦。但係我留意到最新新聞咧，就係會有其中嘅九龍東會有一個項目嘅嚇，但係起我都好擔心咧。有
係得個齋講，因為事實上咧冇咗呢個海港保安條例呢個噉嘅呢個屏障呢個呢個障礙咧。如果唔搞掂佢咧，唔修定咧，始終咧係搞唔掂嘅。如果諗住要修咧，我真係建議橫掂都係咧，唔好去咁遠啦。即係上李顯講嗰啲好多地嘅政策，不如咁啦，觀塘避風塘咧，其實係個好現成嘅一個位置嚟嘅。
搞到連我哋有鐵飯碗之稱嘅公務員團隊、嘅部隊同埋其他文職嘅團隊都話要另外特別優惠咧，可唔可以咧係有啲喺税方面嘅優惠啊？咁嗱，呢個我又翻轉頭個問題啦，即係剛才所講個阿陳德勤陳德勤議員所講嗰個啦，係誒叫做係。
先埋冇感覺嘅。
畀人鬧到嘛嘛聲～
冇人鬧過老闆一句。
都有十幾萬，如果可以攞翻出嚟使嘅話。
哦，噉我而家抹一抹汗之後，繼續講落去。
我哋個政府攞咗成三四千億出嚟。
點解咧？因為就係做得唔好咧。
唔怪得啲同事點解寫咁長嘅稿畀我咧，原來即係有三廿分鐘嘅嚇。
到係低下階層點剷法，同埋嗰個運載點樣？誒。
所以我我想講咧，就係話，而家呢個去到噉，花咗咁多錢去所謂我哋嘅救疫之後咧。
你睇下而家，譬如話，好似睇新聞啦，近期嘅新聞啦，東瀛油人哋炒咗成百一百二十個嗰個誒員工，老闆都拎二千萬出嚟做遣散費。
但係我哋而家已經去到山窮，未至山窮水盡。但係似乎政府都已經覺得自己係山窮水盡啦，唔會再拎錢出嚟，唔會再派錢嘅時候，咁點咧？咁咁當然我哋我不嬲我自己強調，甚至我都多謝包括我哋代主席嘅政黨啦，都係啊一路都支持呢個強資金嘅問題啦。的而且確咧，你話。
啊！我哋而家我明完全明白到嗰個line、嗰官方嗰條線啊，即係話：，唉，我哋個制度完整啊，又話要個嗰個初心係點啊？唉，過到而家先算啦。因為問題就係而家實在太多人已經太慘啦。你依個時候你都唔肯輕輕扭鬆少少咧，幫下啲人咧，我覺得你啊，就真係完全唔知道。
唔識做咧，即係嗰個講法做法，下下都講好多理性喺裏邊咧。即即即係大就咁簡單啫嘛。咁而家我我想再補充我提出嗰幾大訴求啦，因為真係夠鍾誒。唔該啊，考慮下誒。我哋平均而家嗰個M P F帳户有二十四點六萬咧，即係變咗我哋每日。
可以幫下啲手字啦，可以幫手呢個貸款擔保啦，可以政府代供半年啦，誒減下税啦，唔該地租啊、差享啊嗰啲減啦，私業有個印花税可以誒嗰個買率賣率咧可以減啦。誒，當然我哋都唔唔奢望咧會有派發現金啦，但係我即係希望咧就係誒政府咧就。
重估翻我嗰句係非常時期，從來未試過咁慘嘅時候，好多政策好多措施咧，必須係要啊，think outside the box思維以外，太過理性咧，太過乾淨，政治上乾淨嘅話咧，恐怕唔係係唔係一個方法。你唔準我主任，我成日嚇自己，原來我有三十分鐘。
大手部就開始咗啦。
另外咧，我係想講講關於嗰個誒國安法嘅問題。
誒咁呢個，我覺得希望係政府係去做嘅時候，可以考慮埋呢個angle去睇，咁而誒。
根本有我以我大律師經驗咁多年咧，根本有一千個理由唔做。只要你話唔得閒，你話我收貴啲。
於是係，我短中期咧都會拎翻快啲拎翻出嚟，係去做。咁呢個係一個所謂誒，希望有個噉嘅後日啦。你洗面一路岌頭，我多謝佢岌頭。噉啊，等我可以繼續講落去啦。
誒，大家都可能會熱滿啲，就講翻即係噉。誒誒，律政司司長都聽過啦，亦都有同事講過啦，就係關於嗰個誒檢控官嘅問題。我就唔想喺度多講啊，因為我不嬲都。
咁所以我哋誒用一個政治考量嘅話，係咪即係以後誒？如果覺得係政治唔正確咧，我哋有啲類似張子強嘅案件，我哋就唔需要理咧，或者大律師應該唔應該做咧？因為佢哋噉樣做嘅係違反公眾利益咧。
我我依個件事，我覺得好睇嘅。我希望咧就，我都當依之前律政司琴日所講嘅嗰個誒講法咧，就係實上係令到我哋大開眼界嘅嚇。但係真正我反而想誒講嘅咧，就係。
誒用創新嘅方案咧喺嗰個誒喺嗰個誒誒融資方面咧，噉我希望好快睇到佢啲咩創新咧，因為我理解到咧喺我身邊嘅地嘅專家喺度，希望冇講錯嚇誒。
誒，如果而家啲人先開始講話，啊，原來cap ring rule係係漏㗎，噉我一早同你講㗎啦，講咗好多年㗎啦，係我哋嗰啲即係我哋啲反對派大律師們不斷強調咩cap ring rule咩的士規則，話要大律師可以誒唔可以唔接案做。
我講完嗰個N.P.F.啦，亦都提過嗰個誒政府嘅思維方面啦。噉我用開我咧，而家或者去一去咧，就講下我哋嗰個誒明日大魚啊。我知道咧就誒呢個當然係一個遠景嚟啦。我個人亦都覺得係應該係再深入研究落去嘅。不過政府就話而家要一個。
我哋如果有嗰個名日大雨咧，長遠嚟講咁多供應咧，我哋希望咧就好似我哋有啲啊，譬如蕭永清先生好多次講啦，希望可以係千帆並舉，令到咧好多團地嘅有地嘅誒建築商或者係誒地產商咧，佢哋會覺得長遠嚟講咧會係多個供應。
好多原因該唔做，但係今次咧真係哇！今次就真係精彩啦，因為呢個去到一個誒有同事認同呢個係一個即係超級嘅講一套做一套嘅方法啦。因為我哋不嬲都係好誒崇尚英國，佢哋喺法治方面嘅崇高理想誒，會係話要確保每一個。
啊！有需要大律師幫助律師幫助嘅市民咧，都會有一個法律上嘅支持。包括連我哋啲豪型申請咧，都係基呢種原因下咧，我哋使咁多錢落去去做嚇。但係當如果真係政治上嘅時候，唔同你講笑啦，話唔畀唔畀嚟，話壓逼佢壓逼佢。咁呢個咧，好喺將來咧，我我真係覺得。
嗯。
誒。
講解一下呢一樣嘢。
任私作隊有好嘅。
剩翻啲時間唔多咧，我想講少少疫情。
中文呢家嘢咧，就係誒。
你都要讀個個碩士嘅課程咧，但係都係有限嘅啫。
但係作為一個法律嘅工具咧，法律嘅語言咧就恐怕就有少少欠缺。
誒，等到其他個案咧，就或者睇下其他國家嘅經驗點啊，我哋先至好穩陣地去做。
怕真係唔係好足夠，咁呢方面咧就而家我哋嘅理解就係政府似乎話要需要咧係等。
誒國安法咧就係史無前例咧，香港第一次咧有條例咧係誒硬邦邦咧就誒新鮮熱辣咁由由北京掟落嚟香港，我哋係基本上咧冇機會咧係消化咗佢啊。噉我以我有限嘅中國法律嘅知識咧，雖然我都假。
啊，當然我都掂過下少少拉丁咧、拉丁文咧，佢哋更加比英文更加精準添啦。咁但係英文都O K嘅，但係中文真係好多時咧嗰啲字眼咧，令到不係啊，好多遐想嘅。咁呢一方面咧，我知道咧就我哋嘅新任嘅誒首席大法官咧就張繼良法官咧，佢就話我哋司法界都心驚百。
戰係嘛？噉我希望佢依個戰咧係會誒夠可以充分有信心地去把握，因為實際上誒呢個噉嘅國安法咧就令到好多香港人好擔心，國際嘅社會都好擔心。咁呢一方面咧，我就唔想過分地悲觀，但係我都希望律政司咧，你個人又好，你部門又好咧，係可以多啲幫。
手咧喺依度咧，係處理下好多嘅概念上嘅問題，包括連誒即係而家依五大走步之後喺法律上究竟足唔足夠去檢控咧？用啲咩原則咧？當然我明白到咧，我哋唔應該過分地針對每一個個案嚟評論，但係原則上係應該可以按一啲乜嘢嘅考量咧，係達至到有間。
有關嘅拘捕咧，係一個係有法律上基礎咧。噉我我見到政府又唔係好多講，噉我唯有自己就誒扮代表咧，就嘗試都喺網上都解解釋下啦。但係，即係而且講咧，好多人好關心呢一樣嘢，好擔心呢一樣嘢。咁希望咧，有機會嘅時候律政師咧，或者其他適當嘅人選咧，幫我哋。
我一個誒舊嘅同學，佢就係一個香港好出名嘅心臟科醫生，多謝佢咧不斷有啲信息畀我咧，就係關於誒點樣處理好多醫療上嘅問題，因為我我唔完全唔熟唔係專家嚇。不過佢經常質疑一樣嘢就係點解政府咧就誒，當然好多朋好多同事都批評㗎啦，點樣後知後覺？
咧做嘢唔可以有前瞻性咧，唔可以所謂嘅誒針對性去處理咧。咁其中包括我哋而家誒關於講緊最熱門嘅講嗰個誒疫苗嘅問題啦，嗰個誒疫苗嘅問題。施政報告裏邊咧，由於當時可能咧未去到呢個位咧，只係得一個字一段提及到疫苗嘅啫。誒，但係恐
誒。
所以我誒。
噉我都有個同同呢位誒。
導致相約嘅，譬如以色列咁啦，佢哋已經去到差唔多成超過二十percent人已經中咗。
我哋舊年十月廿三號開始嗰個誒字方面嗰個計劃一齊做啦，噉。
嚇咗自己一輪之後咧，我個個稿咧而家都唔知跳咗去邊度。不過我都誒再有時間咧，我輕輕都講少少咧，有關於我哋嗰個誒以往嘅嗰個誒舊我哋嘅市個問題。
政府誒，關於嗰個最近嚇連銷市場咁嗰樣嘢咧，即係幾日之內可以改變，從所謂叫從善漁流啦。我希望政府都喺呢方面咧，可以從善漁流多翻少少咧，令到咧係誒市民咧係覺得係可以真係唔使再喺度捱落去誒。
醫生咧個睇法都一樣，就係有啲嘢我哋係覺得係咪應該唔好等得咁耐、咁過分地穩陣咧？我明白當然牽涉到人命係要需要穩重嘅，但係我哋其實牽涉到其他好多國家咧，已經係誒畀我哋先行先咁多嘅時候，誒譬如好似誒同我哋人口削幾誒。
誒咁而我哋仲喺度一一支都未做嘅啊，噉啊原因係點咧？有個講法就話啲藥啲藥已經喺咗深圳等緊我哋，我唔知係咪我冇冇資料嚇，但係希望政府可以回應嗰陣時可以講講，係我哋有有講法就係話我希望可以做到嗰個電子誒針卡系統搞掂先啦，即係配合翻。
我嘅理解咧就係我哋以往醫生咧，每我哋每一年嘅流感咧都有醫生有出邊嘅私人私人醫生咧幫手做打流打流感針。誒，佢哋大約係我諗每當我哋坊間有一千位私人醫生先咧，每人大約每一年平均打六百支到啦。啊，平均嚇咁如果谷下就最早做咧，去到。
兩三千已經都唔係問題嘅。咁如果佢哋嗰個數字咁做法嘅話咧，好快已經可以打到二三百萬，加埋我哋醫院啊、醫療中心啊、其他部門咧，加埋又多二三百萬咧。其實我哋要做咧係唔難嘅。我想了解係咪真正我哋咁需要咁穩陣，要誒所謂reinvent。
the will咧重新發明個錄咧，我哋人全世界都做曬嗰啲嘢。當歐盟嗰啲車嚟到香港嗰時，我哋唔需要再check嗰啲車安唔安全或者係咪環保。當人哋全世界都用緊呢啲嘅時候咧，我哋係咪應該都應係可以平衡翻嗰個誒急切性同埋嗰個誒穩陣性咧？咁呢方面係咪而家我哋喺過分地？
誒落後咗咧，因為理論上，如果我哋一月份而家已經月頭打咗針嘅月月啊月中月尾打第二針嘅話咧，我哋希望可以過年前咧就已經可以就相當多人咧可以打到係可以誒，起碼打針嘅人咧可以開翻對於嗰啲誒酒樓啊啲嘅其他誒小商户啊。
啊。
誒。
一啲熟悉政治。
呢一排咧就誒。
我哋香港咧，實在太缺乏。
做啲劇嘅角色咧，有時係比較生硬啊，比較。
大家如果睇中央一台咧，就有個節目咧，叫《渡過鴨綠江》。
特別咧，係熟悉內地政治嘅官員。
誒而我哋過往使咗個三千幾億咧，就誒嗰個防疫抗疫基金咧。
幫咗啲啲大機構，幫啲行業，而係幫唔到個別嘅市民，就係救市不救人噉。呢個我亦都希望喺再次提一提咧，希望政府係關注多啲咧。
睇來應該係啲北即係東東歐啊蘇聯人嚟㗎，就扮美國人咧就好唔似嘅。咁但係咧就誒有個信息出咗嚟咧，我希望都或者隨便講講咧，就係。
好，基本上咧，我已經講曬，我要誒寫咗個稿。不過我都趁有我少少時間咧，我都喺度或者誒都講少少誒其他嘢。
提過咧，就我哋希望可以比較多啲前瞻性咧，係會走在疫情前面，而唔係咧就太多樣嘢都係誒誒發生咩事先應變啦。呢個不嬲都我哋都講緊㗎啦。特別當我哋而家睇緊我哋嘅失業率咧，去到六點六個percent咁高咧，大家都都都擔心啦。咁誒。
實或過過境啊、過關啊，都可以做得到咧。咁噉，我哋而家係似乎咩都唔做，等嘅咧。呢個情況令到好多人好焦慮。而事實上，誒誒，我諗都唔需要多講啦。太多人流，即係呢方面話，我哋究竟係做得太慢啦、太少啦，同埋係冇咩方向性。噉我希望或者，與其話係太緊。
將要清零咧，因為清零係當然係一個目標，但係清零其實誒都係希望最主要就係有足夠嘅安全度，令到我哋可以開翻百業，都可以重新工作翻喺個經濟上可以誒復甦翻。咁呢個平衡咧，我覺得係需要咧，係輕輕或者執翻重多少少，就好似。
我哋誒曾經應該係，如果冇記錯應該係司長咧，啊就話我哋即係政策上咧係將持有度啦，咁但係我收到唔少嘅批評咧，就其實話誒就將持有度咧，其實實際寫住做，噉我希望唔係過分地苛刻，因為實。
上咧，誒，正如我剛才所講咧，我哋誒而家畀市民嘅感覺咧，就係我哋誒處理好多經濟上嘅問題又好啊，或者係就業嘅問題又好啊，都係好似係咧，我哋誒公務員就自己一套，就唔係好理市民係應該點樣點樣誒出面點樣慘法誒，亦都係剛才都。
誒不幸地咧，就似畀人感覺咧，就真係補唔到多幾多就業。啊，剛才我都講過嗰啲數字啊，同埋包括最近嗰個誒，譬如好似東瀛遊呢啲噉嘅大嘅旅行社啦嚇，都有又出事啦。而係只不過咧，係曾經使過嗰啲時間咧，落咗去啲錢就去咗嗰啲大機構度咧，係係令到我哋誒畀人感覺只係幫。
我諗在座官員可能就唔係咁得閒會睇啦，睇都可能唔會睇CCTV一啦，或者可能睇啲劇咧都可能睇嗰啲香港啲劇多過睇一啲內地嘅劇。咁當然咧劇集咧就風格上又唔同啦，特別我見到佢哋好多時嗰啲戲咧就當然係國內嘅水準咧，就有時佢特別揾一啲外國。
我會。
的，而且確咧，我哋好多嘢咧。
我哋係錯過咗好多信息。
同埋香港人之間一個好嘅橋梁，多謝主席。
如果冇其他議員想起呢一節發言。
都唔好講國際政治，好多中央啊北誒北京嘅官員畀我哋嘅政治符號啊、政治信息咧，我哋完全接收唔到。
嗱，議員咧，我完全坦白告戒啊！我完全就係耍到無倫嘅，即係我都係我呢啲就係中國政治完全唔識嘅。我哋對於內地對於啊，譬如共產黨啊，對於國對於黨史啊，對於好多發生嘅事咧，都一知半解嘅。我亦都冇陳一勤議員咁勤，你而家睇埋啲明史啊、清史啊噉啊啊多啲嘢睇咧。但係，
噉啊會點咧？好多時我哋嘅官員咧就根本完全係平衡時空嘅。好多時中央政府畀我哋嘅信息咧，我哋係都唔知佢講緊乜，或者佢已經喺度邊啲係虛嘅，邊啲係實嘅，我哋完全收唔到。咁當然我知道個別官員咧，可能就某啲嘅部門咧，特別係嗰啲誒公安啊、國安。
啲部門咧，可能會佢哋嘅交往多啲咧，就會咗多啲偈傾下。但係我哋整體嚟講咧，整體上香港嘅政策咧，好多時咧係完全脱曬內地嗰個做法噉嘅咧，就變咗我哋好多嘢咧係估下估下咧，係估唔到真正幫到香港咧點樣能夠做到一個既可以迎。
合翻中央政府佢哋嘅真正嘅思維，佢哋嘅信息，佢哋嘅期望，但係同時用一個香港市民可以接受到、相信嘅、信服嘅、舒服嘅語言咧，去做一個中央嘅橋梁。咁呢一方面咧，我知道我哋有啲有嗰啲所謂訓練班啊，好多其他嘢，但係都仲係真係未夠。
我哋有冇一啲真係呢方面嘅專長，可以係做顧問咧，可以就係一個組織咧。我希望呢個順便都睇一睇，希望能夠我哋可以加強翻我哋同中央之間嘅一個合作同關係。如果同時咧，唔好過分地咧，就係即係好似鷹母學舌咁咧，中央講咩，我哋香港講乜嘢，而係可以咧做一個中央嗱。